<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Worcester the second of Febr. last being Candlemas day, at the funerall of Mris Alice Tomkins wife unto Mr Thomas Tomkins one of the gentlemen of His Majesties chappell royall. By John Toy, Master of arts and one of the petty canons of the said cathedrall church.</title>
            <author>Toy, John, 1611-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E154_47</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869741</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94777)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E154[47])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Worcester the second of Febr. last being Candlemas day, at the funerall of Mris Alice Tomkins wife unto Mr Thomas Tomkins one of the gentlemen of His Majesties chappell royall. By John Toy, Master of arts and one of the petty canons of the said cathedrall church.</title>
                  <author>Toy, John, 1611-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tomkins, Alicia, d. 1642.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XIV, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156844:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN THE Cathedrall Church of Worceſter the ſecond of Febr. laſt being Candlemas day, at the funerall of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ALICE TOMKINS wife unto M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Tomkins</hi> one of the Gentlemen of his Majeſties Chappell Royall.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN TOY Maſter of Arts and one of the Petty Canons of the ſaid Cathedrall Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the yeere 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:156844:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156844:2"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached in the Cathedrall Church of Worceſter at the funerall of M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> ALICE TOMKINS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOB 14. part of the 14. verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>All the dayes of my appointed time will I wait till my change come.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to deduce this Text by long deſcent from precedent verſes, this whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a ſhort diſcourſe of the courſe of mans life, how full of miſerie! how miſerably ſhort! which holy <hi>Job</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering armes himſelfe with devout reſolve, <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which reſolve may bee reſolved into theſe ſixe heads:
<list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, we have but our time.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, this time is but of dayes, very ſhort.</item>
                  <item>3. Thirdly, this time nor comes, nor goes by chance, but by Divine appointment.</item>
                  <item>4. Fourthly, after this time comes a change, death.</item>
                  <item>5. Fifthly, this change is not terrible, but by all good men to be deſir'd and expected.</item>
                  <item>6. Sixthly, this expectation by <hi>Job</hi>'s example ſhould remaine with us all our daies, <hi>All the dayes, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156844:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156844:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156844:4"/>
            <p n="1">1. Yea indeed? he that is the Map, maſterpiece, and wonder of the world, hath man but this time? Why did God make his chiefeſt veſſell for uſe and honour of ſuch brittle ſtuffe, which would ſerve him but for a ſeaſon? why did he build ſo gloriouſly to throw it downe again ſo ſoon? wherefore would he print his image in common clay? and adorne with ſuch art a piece of mouldring earth? O the pitie, that wormes ſhould pull in pieces ſo Divine a Forme, or that an immortall ſoule ſhould be married to worms meat, a rotten carcaſe; the ſtarres above far beneath man in dignitie hold ſtill their place and ſplendour, and ſhine as cleare as when freſh from the hand of the Creatour; man like a bearded Commet blazeth a while with troubled flame, and anon conſumes to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or rather like the ſparkle flies up with heat, and haſte, as if it meant to viſit the Celeſtiall fires, and vaniſheth by the way within few yards of the earth: If any thing of the vaſt creation were worthy an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall being, man more: yet alas nothing more frail and mutable then he.</p>
            <p>Why? and who may be thanke? himſelfe and his ſinnes. Had he kept that Righteouſneſſe with which God inveſted him in Paradiſe, he had equall'd the dayes of heaven; though this building were of clay, in the calm aire, &amp; ſun-ſhine of Gods favour it might have ſtood for ever; our ſin turned his favour into fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and tempeſt, and ſo our Cottage cannot abide the blaſting of the breath of his diſpleaſure; the ſparke deſerves to die that in pride flies away from the fuell that did feed it, ſo did man; the commet merits darkneſſe that bearded the ſtarres, blazeth with pride and terrour, fils the world with blood and feares, ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156844:4"/>did man; what is the clay fit for but abjection? that hath loſt the ſtampe and image that ennobled it above common dirt. Why ſhould not worms have juſtice, if man treſpaſſe on their kingdome? why may they not avenge it? they have little reaſon to ſpare him; not only theſe Creepers, but even the whole Creatures groane under a curſe for him; that God formed ſo glorious a Creature out of clay, teacheth us his power, who <hi>ex omni ebore</hi> can worke wonders out of meane materials; that he made us of clay, kin to the dung-hill and dirt in the kennels, was to teach man humilitie, nor hath he wrong'd the celeſtiall part the ſoule, by cloathing her in clay, would ſhe keepe it cleane from ſin: God himſelfe deſires no better dwelling, the Son of God Chriſt Jeſus did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine to become man.</p>
            <p>Yea, and we may thank the mercy of God that we are thus confined to time; ſin ſo adheres to our tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nature, that we can never ceaſe to commit, till we be committed to the earth; death doth enlarge us from the ſlaverie of ſinne, ſince the earth is curſt with thornes, our hearts hedg'd with cares, ſince nature is become our ſtepmother, and the good which ſhould ſatisfie our ſoule, withdrawen; it is an happineſſe that we ſhall once die, and ceaſe from our labours; yea <hi>periiſſemus niſi periiſſemus,</hi> we had loſt by our righteouſneſſe, we got by our ſin; the goodneſſe and wiſdome of our God hath wrought a greater weight of Salvation for us, out of our ruines; if the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had ſtood wee had enjoy'd but an earthly Paradiſe, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> hath made us heires of a celeſtiall Inheritance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As this life is but for a time, ſo this time is but of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156844:5"/>dayes, very ſhort. The ſumme is but ſhort, where all the figures are but pence, the journey not long that may be meaſured by Inches; the leaſe may well bee termed little, whoſe date is but for dayes. Were the life of man reckoned by Olympiads, decads, luſters, ages, or yeares, we might expect a ſpatious being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Cradle and the Grave; but there needs no ſuch large Arithmeticke, no puzling compoſition of numbers to fathom the life of man, minutes multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed will make houres, a ſmall paſſage of ours will diſpatch a day, and a few dayes will meaſure the life of man: many doe but juſt looke upon the world, diſdaine, and die: many rather commit patricide, and kill their mothers in the wombe, then they will daigne to looke on ſuch a world. How many come only to ſuck a Bib, or ſhake a Ratle, and returne again to earth? I dare ſay the third part of mankind do not attaine to a moneth.</p>
            <p>Our common phraſe is, <hi>All the dayes of our life,</hi> the ſame phraſe is moſt frequent in holy Scripture, <hi>Jacob</hi> had lived an hundred and thirtie yeares ere he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended into Egypt, yet he cals them but dayes, <hi>Few and evill have my dayes been. Adams</hi> time was called but dayes, though 830. yeares, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.5. They whoſe poſſeſſion is but for their naturall life are allowed in Law to ſet but from three yeares to three yeares, and truly the taker doth preſume, and ſometimes ſuffers for it: well then may we reckon humane life by dayes, when our whole was caſuall and incertaine, and every piece of a day a ſeverall mercy; hence it is (I thinke) that day is declin'd with the doubtfull Gender. But indeed dayes is a large expreſſion, if you will conſider it more narrowly; all is but a day,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156844:5"/>yeſterday was as to day, and to morrow will not much differ, all dayes are ſiſters, ſo like, that there is little or nothing more then a numericall diſtinction between them; he that ſees but one day hath ſeene the Sun ariſe and ſet, he that lingers to an hundred yeares hath ſeene but little more. It is true the yeare like a Gentlewoman varies oft her attire; but the perſon and ſubſtance is alwayes the ſame, and each day the Epitome of our whole life; but me thinkes a day is too much to attribute to man: that is his which he enjoyes, what is that? the time paſt? no, that is dead and gone; the time to come? no, that may never come: the preſent? yea, but what's that? an inſtant point, an <hi>individuum,</hi> an <hi>ens rationis,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of our braine, indeed almoſt nothing: but ſtay, I ſhould goe beyond my Text, if I doe, I doe not goe beyond Scripture. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mine age is nothing unto thee.</hi> Indeed that is halfe a nothing which hath an end, man hath two, our whole ſpace is even juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in reſpect of the dayes of Eternitie: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween finite and infinite is no proportion, looke back on all the time paſt, all the dayes, yeares, and houres are meaſured with one ſudden thought, which is next to nothing.</p>
            <p>The generations of men, ſaith the Poet, are like the ſucceſſion of leaves, which no ſooner are greene, but already turning yellow, and readie to fall. Harke to the Prophets cry; what will he cry? that <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, and the glory thereof as the flower of the field:</hi> riſing, withering, flouriſhing, fading, growing, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, living, dying, as it were all in an inſtant. <hi>David</hi> calls mans life, a ſpanne, a dreame, a vapour, a bubble. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith leſſe, all things ſublunary are vanitie, that is the appearance of nothing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:156844:6"/>
            <p>Till thou canſt enjoy life, 'tis not a life but a being, or at moſt, but as the life of trees, which is without ſence of it ſelfe. We have perhaps ſeventie yeares before us, but little of this doe we enjoy, <hi>minimum est quod vivitur.</hi> Infancy and Childhood is but the portall through which we enter into life, all that while we are not come to our ſelves: in youth we are ſo ſublimed with pride; or ſo vehemently forc'd with headlong paſſion, that all that while we live like madmen, beſide our ſelves, we cannot well be ſaid to live till we arrive at gray haires, and no ſooner do we arrive at that Meridian, but we are mellow and ripe for the grave, and indeed <hi>ſenectus ipſa morbus,</hi> age is nothing but a long diſeaſe, a lingring death.</p>
            <p>Again, of that ſpace we live, how little do we live to our ſelves? halfe of all is conſumed in ſleep, the ſiſter of death (thanks to nature ſo long we are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,) of the reſt, much is worne out in buſineſſe for others, much loſt and laviſht on our pleaſures, ſome ſlips idlely through our fingers, little beſtowed on God, or goodneſſe, almoſt all expended on buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that leaſt concerns us, <hi>diù fuit, non diù vixit,</hi> ſo much we have lived, as we have lived well, and alas how ridiculouſly ſhort are our lives, if meaſured by our goodneſſe?</p>
            <p>O how much are they too blame, that haunt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and hunt after paſtime? (that's the world) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling themſelves of thoſe pretious houres which God hath given them to ſtudie and procure Eternity; alas are the wings of time ſo leaden and lazie that we ſhould adde and impe more feathers to it? time lacquies with the motions of the heavens; and they are as ſwift as thought, the Sun one of the lower and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156844:6"/>ſlower Planets, moves not leſſe then foure thouſand miles every minute; if you are ſure of heaven, ſpur on, delude time as you liſt: but if not, O why ſhould you haſten your miſery.</p>
            <p>O how much to blame is the covetous man, he not conſidering how ſhort his time is, rakes and toiles to heap up a miskin of wealth, as if he meant to live for ever; what doth he think to continue ſtill? why? there is a ſtatute of mortalitie againſt him, <hi>Statutum est ſemel mori.</hi> Doth he think to bribe death? it will not be, <hi>Mors aquo pede pulſat pauperum tabernas, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gúmque turres.</hi> The rich man died alſo; doth he think to carry it with him? no, we muſt not allow tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of our money to hell, <hi>nudus venit,</hi> naked he came, naked he muſt return. What, will he lay it up for his children? I thinke he that truly loves mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney little thinks of that: if he did (marry) he would doe them a great pleaſure to leave them curſed wealth to undoe them; he will lay it up for his old age, and then enjoy it, leaſt of all; <hi>quo minus via, eo plus viatici,</hi> covetouſneſſe is fierceſt in the cloſe, he will rather choke himſelf with cares, or ſtarve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, not daring to diminiſh his mouldy god, his treaſure.</p>
            <p>Since our time is ſo ſhort a Kalendar of a day, O how much too blame is the intemperate glutton, and drunkard, that drink away their health, and fill their body with diſeaſes; every intemperate draught is but a ſweet poyſon, the glutton eates his knife, and God may juſtly challenge them of ſelf murder, that thus will eate and drinke in ſpight of health and nature, and ſo ſhorten that precious time, which God indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for better purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:156844:7"/>
            <p>Is life ſo ſhort at utmoſt extenſion, O curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men that delight in bloud, that like <hi>Atropos</hi> make a trade of killing, butchers of their brethren, traytors to nature, why ſhould we cut that thread which another will ſhortly cut? why ſhould we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy our Brethren a little light? why ſhouldeſt thou envie light to thy ſelf? thy thread (murderer) is twiſt with his whom thou ſlayeſt, juſt vengeance hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, <hi>the bloudy minded man ſhall not live out half his dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is life ſo ſhort? why then being mortall doe we nouriſh immortall hatred againſt our Brother? hath he done thee wrong? forbear the fault, the ſentence of death is upon him; anon the worms will pull him all to peeces, what greater revenge canſt thou deſire? <hi>dum luctamur, aderit immortalitas;</hi> ſpight of all thy ſpight death will diſarm the, &amp; make thee lye quietly in the grave with thy contemned Brother. If life be ſo ſhort? why doe we poſt off repentance, and make ſo little care to prepare for the preſence of the Judge and hazard our ſalvation to the extreameſt minutes? how many that long ſince might have been raked up in the grave, are but beginning to live? nay 'tis not ſo well, they doe but ſay they will begin, but let him that means to goe to heaven, ſet out betimes, leſt like the fooliſh boy we game out the candle which ſhould light us to bed; time paſt will not be recalled, and we have a ſpatious diſtance to diſpatch in a few mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, how ſhort and uncertain ſoever our dayes are to us, with God they are determined and appointed: ſo ſaith my Text, <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God Almighty hath ſet up bounds which wee cannot paſſe, and untill that houre which he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156844:7"/>doe approach, we cannot dye: this paper body of ours is proofe againſt all violence; to this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees that of <hi>Job</hi> (above) <hi>thou haſt made my dayes, as the dayes of an hireling;</hi> the hireling is but for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time. That of <hi>Salomon, There is a time to be borne, and a time to dye,</hi> this appears by this, that many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us are Prophets, and have with certain predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction pointed out the time of their departure, if their departure were not definite and certain, how could they foreſee when they ſhould expire?</p>
            <p>This more eſpecially appears by our many haire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bredths eſcapes of death and danger, who is alive to day, that hath not been often at the gates of death? <hi>Joſeph</hi> was thrown into the pit, the pit did not ſhut her mouth upon him; <hi>Daniel</hi> to the Lions, the Lions did not open their mouth to hurt him; <hi>Moſes</hi> tottered in an Arke of ſedge, that ſimple boat brought him a ſhore, and landed him in the armes of a Princeſſe; the three children were thrown into the furnace, the fire could not ſinge them; <hi>Jonah</hi> in the tempeſtuous ſea, all the waters would not drown him; <hi>Paul</hi> was in perils oft, in death oft, yet ſtill reſerved a ſacrifice for <hi>Rome;</hi> how oft ſtood <hi>Caeſar</hi> in the face of death amongſt his enemies to be at laſt ſlain in the Capitoll by his friends; how many deaths did that Romane avoid to be at laſt choakt with a haire; how many come ſafe from battle over the dead bodies of thoſe that ſtood round about them; behold how the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that walks in darkneſſe, picks, and chooſeth out of ſome frequent families but one; out of others all but one. Who would not admire how thoſe floate upon the deepe three or foure years within three or foure inches of death, where every wind and wave
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156844:8"/>threatens death, yet return with ſafety to the ſhore; yea in a common ſhipwrack how many have the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken peeces of the veſſel ſaved, when the whole one could not? what was all this, chance? let Atheiſts and Heathens ſay ſo, we Chriſtians muſt explode it, certainly it appears to me by this that God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath allotted each man his fate, which no danger how great, or near can alter.</p>
            <p>That to every man is an appointed time, appears alſo in part by this, that the ſhadow of death flies him that purſues it, and follows him that would fly it, death hovers over him that delights in life, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines him that deſpiſeth it. It ſeems death dare not ſtrike, but like the Clock, till the juſt numbers of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes be accompliſhed. Why elſe ſhould he not come, when called and importuned? I have heard ſome diſdaine, and call death partiall, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die; I have ſeen him hit others in the height and vigour of ſtrength, and beauty, with unexpected and moſt unwelcome ſtroke; the yong and frolike bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock falls for the ſhambles, the old oxe reſerved to groan in the accuſtomed yoke.</p>
            <p>Nor ſeems it any wonder to me, that man ſhould be appointed his time, he was not born at his owne appointment, much leſſe is it fit that he ſhould dye at his own diſcretion. The keyes of life and death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God. If it be in my power to grant the leaſe, it is alſo of my right to limit the time. 'Tis not man alone, that hath his time appointed, but even e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very creature; the ſparrow falls not to the ground but by Gods decree: yea, the whole creature, there is a day and hour ſet downe, when the whole world ſhall determine, when the Elements ſhall melt, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156844:8"/>Moon be turned to bloud, the Sunne eclipſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the great Machin of the world ſhaken and diſſolved. From the conſideration of this point, wee may make to our ſelves theſe wholeſome uſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt not to love life too much, not to be too anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſollicitous to produce and extend it; nor to truſt in diet, herbs, aire, or art; as if length of dayes were to be had from hence. Let us not like <hi>Aſa,</hi> ſeek to a ſecond; firſt the phyſitian rather then the Lord, Let us look up to Jehovah, ſubmit our ſelves to his pleaſure, and appointment. Let us not preſume of that which is not in our power, but refer our ſelves to God, and accept of every day as a new life, and mercy; <hi>Grata ſuperveniet quae non ſperabitur hora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond uſe is of patience to wait the Lords lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and ſalvation; not like the freſh bullock to ſhake the yoke of affliction, &amp; make it worſe by our anger, bear thine affliction patiently, tis by his appointment. Wilt thou not ſuffer a little for the Lords ſake? the Lord Jeſus ſuffered all afflictions for thee; nay, but it is appointed for thy ſake, out of this furnace thou wilt come like gold refined, this fire was but to purge thy droſſe, and burniſh thee for heaven. <hi>Shall we receive of God good and not evill?</hi> Shall we not wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the evil that comes for our good? be patient a while, anon thy pain will ceaſe; 'tis our a finite evill our dayes have their date, our life anon determines, this heavy night may have a cheerfull morn. <hi>Dabit Deus his quoque finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third uſe is againſt too much mourning for the dead, this is our great fault, we mortals love mortall things, as if the fruition and uſe were immortall. Me thoughts it was a brave voice of that Romane, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156844:9"/>at report of his ſonnes death, ſaid, <hi>Scio me mortalem genuiſſe,</hi> I knew I did not beget a God, that could not dye. Thy friend is dead, what hath he loſt? his leaſe is expired, he had his time appointed; thou deſervedſt to looſe, that wouldſt build on leaſe-hold as tenure free for ever. <hi>Cadant lacrymae, non fluant,</hi> let tears fall not flow. Can the hot waters of thy tears recover him? the voice of thy grones awake him? Thy friend is dead, couldſt help? canſt recall him? that griefe is to no purpoſe which will doe no good. I will allow you to ſhed a few tears over the herſe, as a ceremony of your friends funerall, and a monument of your love, that you are not flint, or iron, but men ſenſible of others evils, endued with naturall affection; no farther. But why ſhould we mourn? our friend is not loſt, but gone before, anon thou muſt goe the ſame way: if he did thee wrong to dye before thee, forgive him, he will never doe ſo any more; thou wilt anon ſhew others the ſame trick, kick up the heeles, and lead others mourning after thy hearſe. Thy friend is not dead, but ſleepes, diſturbe not his reſt with thy noiſe. Thy friend is not dead, but divided, and like a foule watch taken aſunder, his materials remain. Thy friend is not dead, but changed, ſo my Text cals death, <hi>All the dayes of mine appointed time will I wait till my change come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Mutability and mortalitie like ice and water beget each other; man was at firſt perfect but muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; his mutabilitie made him mortall, and his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie makes him again mutable; by this change <hi>Job</hi> muſt needs underſtand death. 'Tis true, man, as if he had been the ſonne of the Moone is full of change, no one man is two dayes alike: the weather varies
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156844:9"/>oft, the face of Heaven is ſometimes lowring, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſerene, ſometime maskt with clouds, ſometimes bathed in miſts; man varies with the weather, yea and more then the weather, now he is calme and temperate, anon he is clouded with cares, one while he is gladſome and cheerfull, then the Sun ſhines; another time chafed and angry, then it thunders; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while he weeps, then it rains; but this change of the Text follows all our appointed dayes, which is onely death. Death is a great change indeed. Firſt we change from health to ſickneſſe, then our cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full looks are changed into ghaſtly paleneſſe, our ſtrength into pain and weakneſſe, the whole man into another man, happy if into a new man. The next change is from ſickneſſe to death, a great change in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: our handſome habits are changd into a ſhroud, our habitation into a Coffin, our Lands into a Grave, nay we into our Lands; our lively heat into an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting cold, our mirth into ſable mourning, <hi>Man goes unto his long home, and the mour ners walke about the ſtreets,</hi> the Bells ring of theſe changes; by this the Family changeth too, the Wife is become a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the ſonne fatherleſſe, the maſter without a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, the ſervant maſterleſſe; theſe changes once in fifty yeers renew the face of the world. Death doth change a marriage into a divorce; life is the union of the ſoul and body, death the ſeparation; the ſoul is ſent back to her heavenly Father, the body to her Mother, the Earth; this is a great change in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that two that lived ſo long, and ſo lovingly ſhould be ſeparated ſo long, and into places ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote.</p>
            <p>Death is a change of a compounded body into his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156844:10"/>native principles; the Aire receives our breath, the Sun our heat, the Sea our moiſture, the Earth that which we had of her, our duſt; theſe Elements which were ere while knit in one common building are now diſtructed into all the world; where will you look for the parcels of your dead friend, his breath perhaps helps to drive a ſhip in ſome remote Sea, his moiſture perhaps went up into the graſſe which grew on the grave, and the Horſe hath eate it, you muſt look quickly for the reſt of his carcaſe, ere the worms have eate it, perhaps the fiſher hath baited his weels with the worms that fed on your friend; here is a change indeed.</p>
            <p>Death is a change from variety of forme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition into all alike; among the living there is much difference, one is noble, another baſe; in death <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> as great as <hi>Manſolus, Menippus</hi> as good a man as great <hi>Alexander;</hi> In this life ſome are rich, the reſt poore; In death there is not reſpect of riches, the carcaſe of <hi>Irus</hi> may boldly ſtink by <hi>Craeſus</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any offence; Among the living ſome are faire, ſome ill-favoured, among the dead there is not a pin to chooſe between <hi>Sappho</hi> and <hi>Hellen, Therſites</hi> and <hi>Aeneas,</hi> all are bald pate, hollow-eyed, flat noſed, chap fallen, and grim alike; Amongſt us there is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of wits, one is ſharp and ſubtle, another blunt and ſimple, let them lye a little in the grave toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you will not diſcern the wiſe man from the foole, the grave Politician from the canting beggar. If that this change were much in our mind, who then would be proud of wealth, that anon muſt be ſtript of all; of wit, whoſe fine head muſt be filled with muſty mould; of birth, that muſt deſcend into
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156844:10"/>the bowels of the earth; of beauty, which will wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into deformitie; of his perſon, which lice and wormes muſt eate; of any thing, ſince anon all will be alike; the worſt in the world as good as he.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But yet Beloved, this change is no robbery, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we ſuffer a little, we ſhall not looſe by it; we are not leſſe men with God, he numbers and reckons the dead, he is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> We cannot looſe by this diſſolution, it is impoſſible that any thing ſhould periſh into nothing, elſe there would be vacuity, and God muſt create a new to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the loſſe; no, the earth will give back our duſt, the Sun our heat, the aire our breath, the water our moiſture; each part of the world each part of every man, and the dead ſhall live againe. Obſerve <hi>Jobs</hi> bleſſed confidence, <hi>I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh, not with other but with theſe ſame eyes:</hi> how poſſible is it to preſume a reſurrection, when God Almighty that ſo made us at firſt out of nothing, hath now all the former materials, and the ſoule entire, ready and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the work? Nay we are ſo far from looſing by this change, that we get much by it; to change la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for eaſe and reſt, is a good bargain; life is torne and diſtracted with many cares, in the grave is no noiſe or diſturbance, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead, they rest from their labours;</hi> to change corruption for incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is a great bargaine, the lying in the Grave doth draine away our poyſon and corruption, and returns it pure and perfect; to change a leaſe of few yeers into a free, and perpetuall tenure is great gaine, by dying we turn our Copy-hold for life into life immortall; to change the world for Chriſt is a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious advantage, all things compared to Chriſt are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156844:11"/>loſſe and dung, by being diſſolved we come to Chriſt; In a word, if glorious and crowned liberty be better than continuall bondage, if a ſtate triumphant be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a militant, if fulneſſe be better than famine, and ſubſtance than ſhadow, heaven than the dunghill earth, and eternitie than doubtfull time; then are we much better, and more happy by this change of death; Hence it is that holy <hi>Job</hi> looks and longs for this change, as he ſaith in my Text, <hi>All the dayes of my appointed time,</hi> &amp;c. Of this one word.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If <hi>Job</hi> waits for the ſalvation of God, then hath he faith towards him, for we doe not wait for that which we thinke will not come; If wee will make this change of death happy and beneficiall unto us, we muſt like <hi>Job</hi> expect the mercy of God, beleeve <hi>that he is, and that he is a faithfull rewarder of them that ſeeke him;</hi> that this God hath ſalvation in his hand for them that will ſtretch forth the hand of faith to receive it from him.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Job</hi> wait, then hath he hope to receive, all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation is mixed with hope, if heaven be not hoped for, it cannot happen to us; if we want this anchor, we may oft try to land, and be as often driven back in the troubles of the labouring deep.</p>
            <p>This expectation cannot be without contented patience; He that is impatient will not wait, <hi>You have heard of the patience of Job,</hi> you know the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and patience of the Lambe Chriſt Jeſus. If we will follow him, we muſt take up our croſſe, if we will raigne, we muſt ſuffer, it is fit we ſhould ſuffer ſomewhat, for glory in heaven were cheap and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, if we might attain it eaſily.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:156844:11"/>
            <p>This waiting and expectation ſuppoſeth prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every one that hath this hope, faith the Apoſtle, purgeth himſelfe, as he is pure. How doe we waſh, and combe, and trimme our ſelves, when call'd to ſome honourable Feaſt; and thinke wee that the King of Heaven will accept into his glorious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and immortall Dainties, them which have not waſht their hands in innocencie? and made them fit for ſuch a Feaſt? the Feaſt is worth the waiting for, 'tis Immortalitie; the Author of the Feaſt hath long waited for us, we had need to waite with oile in our Lampe; we know not when the Bridegroome will knocke, we cannot doe better then to wait, this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Expectation will ſwallow up, or ſweeten all our preſent calamitie, we have nothing elſe to doe but to wait; indeed we ſhould doe nothing elſe, and <hi>Bleſſed are they whom the Lord when he commeth ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme of all amounts to this, God with his glorious Angels is comming to us, he ſends his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours before him, to tell and warne us of his comming, He tarries a while to try our Faith and Patience, He tarries a while to give us time to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for his comming, that comming and finding us prepared he may crowne us with immortall glory.</p>
            <p>Thus beloved have I haſtned through a ſpatious Text, and 'twas fit I ſhould, Brevitie was the main ſubject thereof, and he that is comming might for ought we know have come ere I had diſpatcht it; Pleaſe you now to wait while I ſpeak a word or two to this ſad occaſion of our meeting, and ſo I will diſmiſſe you.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:156844:12"/>
            <p>We are met here to doe the laſt honour to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Siſter, and in her name I thanke this worthy Aſſembly that come to wait on her deſerved Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies; would ſhe had a better Orator, this preſence, eſpecially this ſubject deſerved it; my happineſſe is the goodneſſe of the ſubject will help out my imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Oratory. I know by her no infirmities that I ſhould need to hide or colour; I need not racke, or torture my invention to force her a praiſe; I neede not ſtraine or diſſemble a ſyllable; ſhe hath filld my mouth with true and reall honour.</p>
            <p>This Text is true in her, we have our time, ſhe had hers, God be thanked a time of peace and plenty; our time is ſhort, 'tis true, hers was neere foureſcore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt two luſters beyond the age of man, if we reckon the number of dayes, and innumerable grievances of life; ſhe lived long I muſt confeſſe, but if we mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure her life by the affection of her friends, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, they will I know confeſſe with me, that hers was too too ſhort, ſhe died much too ſoone. Our time is appointed, ſo was hers; ſhe was not cut off by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely chance, ſhe ſhortned not her dayes by intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate diet, ſhe long enjoyed a quiet and entire old age, and like an undiſturbed taper burnt out to the laſt weeke, yea a good while ſince with prophetique prediction ſhe points out the time of her departure. We ſhall have our change, ſhe hath wained ſome few weekes and now hath hers, from corruptible to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, from mortall life to life immortall, from the light of this world, by which we ſee a world of miſerie, to the light of Heaven, and Righteouſneſſe, which ſhall never be changed, obſcured, nor eclipſed.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:156844:12"/>
            <p>This for her we may well preſume, for my owne part I deſire from my ſoule my laſt end may be like unto hers, with firme faith, cheerefull hope, ſettled patience, and perpetuall preparation, ſhe waited, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, called, and invited Chriſt. So farre with my Text, but I ſhould wrong her much to ſay no more, ſhe was an excellent neighbour, I ſpeake it before them that know it, and have moſt ingeniouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it, ſhe was gratefull to the beſt, gratious to the poore, peaceable, officious and affable to all.</p>
            <p>She was an excellent wife, witneſſe the many tears her husband ſhed, truer teares I dare ſay never fell at funerall; witneſſe his charge, and charitie to bring her home with honour. She like that Embleme of a good Houſwife was ſeldome farre from home, at home moſt neatly induſtrious, but eſpecially ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to her husband, that where to patterne ſuch ſweet conjugall Societie I profeſſe I know not; Let us learne it, (beloved,) beleeve it, it is a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for heaven to be well skill'd in the dutie of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; this marriage is but for a time, death will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce it, the ſecond time we ſhould be married to Chriſt, and will he wed them to himſelfe whom he knew froward and unchaſte to a former Spouſe? This true good tree hath borne good fruit to the honour and good of this Church, they that have taſted it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, have praiſed it for a fragrant and gracious ſavour, not many Orchards afford the like; ſhe was happy in it to the laſt.</p>
            <p>But which is above all, ſhe was a very good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, witneſſe her meekneſſe, one of the trueſt markes of a Chriſtian, meek ſhe was as appeared by her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron-like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156844:13"/>plainneſſe; ſo meeke, that ſhe ſcorn'd not to hold diſcourſe with a Child that could ſcarce ſpeake againe to her, an argument of that childiſh innocency by which we attaine heaven.</p>
            <p>A good Chriſtian ſhe was, witneſſe that great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of her devotion, ſhe lived like <hi>Anna</hi> as it were continually in the Temple, twice a day for many decads of yeares, ſhe attended the worſhip of God Almightie in this Church, nor would ſhe leave that holy uſe, for age and weakneſſe, but ſpight of ſickneſs, as if ſhe meant to ſacrifice her life to God, ſhe came ſtill, till the heavie weight of death detained her in her bed.</p>
            <p>For her Charity, a main part of the eſſence of a <hi>Christian;</hi> I muſt ſay for that part of Charity that pertains to the tongue, in judging and cenſuring, ſhe did excell, ſhe loved not to hear, ſhe abhorred to ſpeak evill of any, ſhe would give fair and candid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to all actions, loving and reverend counſell to all that came neer her. As for the Charitie of her purſe, I know not what it was, nor indeed was it her deſire that any ſhould know; but this know, ſhe bred up Orphanes, ſent often meat, and money to her ſick neighbours, her ſervant hath been ſeen to diſtribute good pieces of money to many poor families from yeer to yeer, from houſe to houſe, I am ſure if it were known who ſent it, it was the ſervants fault, for ſhe charged her the contrary; ſhe loved (happy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) to hide her treaſure, and keep the left hand ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what the right had done. I am fain to glean and gueſſe at her Charity, ſurely if all were knowne, it would amount to a great ſumme, and her great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156844:13"/>glory, ſhe rather deſired that God might have the glory, to whom of due it belongs. Goe to the earth bleſſed Earth, and ſleep there ſweetly, till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, thy other part is ere this ſafe arrived to the boſome of <hi>Abraham:</hi> Bleſſed Lord, give us grace ſo to follow her holy example, that we may at laſt come to thoſe unſpeakable joyes, which thou haſt prepared for all them that unfainedly love thee, and expect thy comming. <hi>Even ſo come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen. <hi>Soli Deo gloria.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:156844:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:156844:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
